RAMANJANEYULU KATAKAM

HR Business Partner | Talent Development & Management | Strategic Planning +919603166746, ramanji222@gmail.com, Hyderabad, India

Summary

Seasoned HR Business Partner with 10+ years of experience in strategic workforce planning, performance management, talent development & Management, Employee Experience and Retention, Talent Engagement, Learning & Development. Successfully led HR initiatives tied to business objectives, resulting in significant improvements in employee engagement and positive work culture. Looking forward to contributing profound HR expertise and passion for workforce innovation to support organizational growth.

Skills

Strategic Workforce Planning, Performance appraisal Management, Succession Planning, Talen Recruitment, Employee Engagement, Talent Management, HR Policies, Change Management, Data Management & Analysis, Compensation & Benefits administration, Employee Relations, Training & Development, Payroll Management, Employee Life Cycle Management, Contract Labor Management, Manpower Vendor Management, End to End Recruitment, Disciplinary mechanism, Grievance & conflict resolution, Employee Connects, Employee satisfaction & experience surveys, Attrition management & Analysis, exit interviews & stay interviews, stake holder management

Experience

Mahindra Logistics Ltd

Hyderabad, India 10/2023 – 05/2024

HR Manager

- Directed a team to implement innovative recruitment strategies, improving the applicant tracking system, which resulted in increasing qualified candidate flow.
- Developed comprehensive succession planning program, leading to improvement in internal promotion rates.
- Spearheaded employee engagement initiatives that reduced staff turnover by 20%, enhancing the company's performance culture.
- Coordinated with cross functional teams to align workforce planning with strategic objectives, achieving a 98% fulfillment rate.
- Managed compensation and benefits policy revamp, increasing market competitiveness and employee satisfaction scores by 25%.
- Ensured timely service delivery as per defined SLAs/KPIs and drive operational efficiency and continuous improvement and Accountable for data management and data accuracy.
- Working with compliance team to manage unrest at few places and accordingly working out on any notices received from Labor department
- Managing and resolving employee relations issues. Maintain a positive work environment, driving employee engagement activities
- Successfully managed disciplinary mechanism and resolved employee grievances &conflicts
- Successfully managed client HR audits and ensured 100% compliance with labor laws.
- Implemented a talent development program tailored to operational executives, improving strong leadership pipeline.
- Verifying Daily & Timely submission of employee attendance. Track Payroll & Leave and absence Management in HRIS every day. Ensure timely disbursement of salary if any missing cases.

Amazon Seller Services Pvt Ltd

WFS Coordinator – HR OPS

Hyderabad, India 01/2022 - 10/2023

- Collaborated with operations for strategic manpower planning, optimizing efficiency.
- Managed vendor relationships and oversaw hiring processes to meet operational needs.
- Implemented strategies to address attrition and conducted related analyses.
- Facilitated smooth onboarding processes and provided necessary support documentation.
- Oversaw end-to-end employee lifecycle management for fulfilment centers in Hyderabad.
- Partnered with operations to align manpower requirements and strategies.
- Maintained applicant information in the Application Tracking System, ensuring completeness and accuracy.
- Resolved employee relations issues and promoted a positive work environment.
- Successfully managed disciplinary mechanism and resolved employee grievances & conflicts
- Led training and development initiatives to enhance employee skills.
- Conducted data analysis to identify trends and suggest improvements for problem areas.
- Overseeing policy implementation and development within the assigned business unit, ensuring adherence to labor laws.

Amazon Transportation Services Pvt Ltd (Quess Corp Payroll) Assistant Manager HR

Vijayawada, India 08/2016 – 01/2022

- Collaborated with department heads to understand business needs and execute recruitment strategies.
- Managed end-to-end recruitment processes, including sourcing, onboarding, and hiring.
- Conducted employee engagement activities and recognition events including FGDs, one one meeting's.
- Ensured compliance with labor laws and managed employee relations.
- Oversaw HR operations, including time and attendance management, performance reviews, and statutory compliance.
- Successfully managed disciplinary mechanism and resolved employee grievances & conflicts
- Provided MIS support for attrition analysis and other HR-related metrics.
- Maintained dashboards for tracking various HR metrics.
- Acted as a primary point of contact for HR-related issues for the AP region.
- My role involved implementing and developing policies within the assigned business unit, while also ensuring adherence to labor laws
- Verifying Daily & Timely submission of employee attendance. Track Payroll & Leave and absence Management in HRIS every day. Ensure timely disbursement of salary if any missing cases.

Mahindra Rural Housing Finance Ltd

Associate HR

Vijayawada, India 11/2014 – 07/2016

- Managed end-to-end recruitment processes for Andhra Pradesh and Telangana regions.
- Facilitated employee engagement activities and induction programs.
- Handled employee relations and lifecycle management.
- Ensured timely completion of documentation and onboarding processes.
- Coordinated with various departments for payroll and statutory compliance.
- Conducted exit interviews and managed exit formalities.
- Conducted stay interviews to identify pulse and retention of employees
- Provided HR-related MIS reports to management.
- Overseeing implementing policies within a specific business unit, while also ensuring that the policies adhered to labor laws.
- Maintaining Dashboards regarding exits, transfers, confirmations, joining, and source of recruitment. Maintaining and giving all HR related MIS to the superiors on time.
- Be the primary contact between the Management and employees
- Administering the employee benefits
- Successfully managed disciplinary mechanism and resolved employee grievances & conflicts
- Verifying Daily & Timely submission of employee attendance. Track Payroll & Leave and absence Management in HRIS every day. Ensure timely disbursement of salary if any missing cases.

IVRCL Infrastructures Ltd

Assistant Officer – HR Trainee

Hyderabad, India 10/2013 – 06/2014

- Coordinating with all HR departments to support in the required areas
- Responsible for documentation, joining formalities, induction & orientation.
- Involving in payroll process.
- Resolving gueries of employees gueries and addressing them one time
- Creating and managing the employee's personnel files.
- Coordinating with the performance appraisals to complete the process on time
- Coordinating in F & F settlements of leaving employee's from the organization
- Responsible for conducting exit interviews.
- Taking care of attendance, leave & absence of the employee's
- Responsible for Monthly MIS Reports.

Maximus HR Pvt Ltd

Recruitment Consultant

Bangalore, India 05/2013 - 11/2013

- Responsible for end-to-end recruitment
- Conducted recruitment drives, sourcing candidates for various roles.
- Coordinated interviews and selection processes for clients.
- Provided HR consulting services to clients on recruitment strategies.
- Managed candidate databases and ensured timely follow-up.

Education

Acharya Nagarjuna University

Guntur, India
Master's degree in Human Resources

2010 - 2012

Chaitanya Bharati Degree College (Affiliated to ANU)

Bachelor's degree in Computer Science

2006 - 2009

HRIS implementation/Transmission/Change Management Projects

- 1. Team member in Implementation of Biometrics in Amazon
- 2. Team member in Implementation of ALLSEC module for off-role WFS HR team, pan India in Amazon
- 3. Implemented SWAYAM tech tool for 3P employees hiring for both internal HR teams & external manpower vendors for newly formed department called WFS in Amazon
- 4. HRIS transmission project from current module to new module (AllsecTech to Cronos) in Amazon

Technical Acumen

- MS Office Suite, Advanced Excel, MIS Analysis, SQL basics.
- SAP R3, Allsec Tech HR, My-time Cronos, Biometric systems. Darwin Box (Nectar), EMSPHERE.
- Trained in ORACLE HCM Fusion Cloud Functional consultant

Achievements

- Recognized by AMAZON continuous 3 quarters as candidate champion for reduced the early attrition from 35% to 15% within targeted guardrail by doing best engagement & employee connect, exit and stay interview activities
- Recognized by AMAZON continuous 3 quarters as DEI beacon for improved the DEI percentage in overall HC (improved from 35% to 55% of DEI in fulfillment center)
- Recognized by AMAZON as NAIL the PLAN for effective work force planning (maintain the 100% fill
 rate in hiring as per operational requirements with quality & stable manpower with reduced
 attrition).
- Recognized by AMAZON as GOING BEYOND for acted as SME & UAT team member to the newly launched HRIS implementation project for recruitment called SWAYAM to test bugs and create learning docs on the process approach for the pan India users and manpower vendors
- Successfully managed payroll accuracy project for the zone and maintained 100% payroll accuracy and reduced supplementary payments and improved metric for the Zone in Amazon.
- Successfully done OT control project and reduced OT consumption throughout the zone and reduced cost of Rs. 3,00,000/- for the zone per month and improved metric score for the zone.

Courses

- Six Sigma Black Belt | International Council for Quality (ICFQ) | November 2022
- Six Sigma Green Belt | International Council for Quality (ICFQ) | October 202

TRAINING & ACADEMIC PROJECTS

❖ IVRCL Limited Training | Trainee (April - June 2012)

 Worked on "Performance Management System" project, reporting to HRD Head, Acharya Nagarjuna University.

Academic Projects

- Performance Management Study, IVRCL Ltd: Analyzed and reported on the company & performance management practices post 4th semester.
- HRM Internship, CAPOL, Chirala: 21-days focus on HR operations and practices during the 3rd semester.
- Government Organization Fieldwork: Explored HRM practices at E.P.F, E.S.I, & I.F over 15 days in the 2nd semester.
- Industrial Visits: Visited 6 companies to observe their operations, 1st semester